[Laughter]
so hello everybody oh can you just go on
mute if you're not speaking sorry I'm
just going to do a bit of an
introduction um so welcome to the third
um morph stream series the others are on
YouTube if you've not had a chance to
catch those so just a reminder of the
purpose of these meetings are to educate
and Inspire at the intersection of
active inference and neuromorphic
Computing um if you've not met me before
I'm Sarah Hamburg so I'm predominantly a
neuroscientist I did my PhD neuroscience
at UCR which is where I first came
across active inference um and I've just
finished a postto in neurom morit
Computing and I'm part of the Sab for
the active inference Institute and I've
think I've been involved with them since
about 2020 when I was trying to work out
earlier but I'm really pleased today
that we're joined by Professor Annan sub
money so he's an assistant professor in
the Department of computer science at
Royal Holloway London he's broadly
interested in learning and intelligence
so that's both algorithmic and
biological his current research is
focusing on understanding the principles
of scalability in deep learning which is
what he'll be talking about today sorry
I'm just admitting some people um so he
aims to use principles of scalability to
build models that are more efficient and
can scale up seamlessly his research
draws inspiration from neuroscience and
biology in his Quest To Build a Better
and more General artificial intelligence
and you can visit his website onand
subber money for more information I'll
pop that in the chat as well so his talk
today is on principles of scalability
and biological Inspirations he's going
to talk about how current models scale
and what we can learn from the
efficiency of biological brains one of
the central themes will be sparsity its
significant role in scalable systems and
its synergies with neuromorphic Hardware
he'll present existing ideas based on
spiking networks and recent work from
his group which is focused on using
various forms of sparity and distributed
learning to improve the scalability and
efficiency of our learning models so the
format will be that the first part um
arnand will speak and then we'll sort of
have a more General open conversation
between all of us um arand I don't know
if you want people to in interrupt you
with questions or not if you just want
to take them at the end that's entirely
up to you yeah I'm actually completely
fine with taking questions during the
talk cool okay right well without
further Ado uh yeah we'd love to hear
your
presentation yeah thank you Sarah and
thank you very much for the invitation
uh so yeah like Sarah mentioned I'm
going to be talking about principles of
scalability and biological
Inspirations uh so I've been working
with computation neuroscience and
machine learning for quite a long time
and have been thinking about uh well I
mean how intelligence Works to some
extent but also really
uh a big part of it is about
understanding how various how biological
models scale and by extension how
artificial intelligence model scale and
that's what I'm going to be talking
about today so just to start off with uh
things that we already
know I mean so AI is really starting to
become better than humans at lots of
things right so this is kind of like a a
plot of performance of various AI models
in relation to humans and you see that
handwriting recognition and speech
recognition image recognition so this
all of these have been like improving
very very fast uh but recently things
like language understanding and reading
comparation have also in imp improved
and become better than humans so there
is really some kind of like a
major movement going on in AI where
things are really becoming uh better
very fast and so the question is what is
happening or why does it so work so well
so there have been a lot of uh advances
in the past do decades uh because we've
started using deep neural networks with
lots of layers and lots of parameters
and we have uh as as a the machine
Learning Community has figured out how
to train these models well and get them
to work well so there has been
algorithmic advances in stochastic
radient descent using Rao layer skip
connections normalization layers and all
of these have been like very important
in
giving us the ability to train these
very deep
networks the other aspect uh that's
things the other thing that has changed
in the past two decades is that we have
lots more data right so we have access
to a lot more data so uh which helps a
lot with supervised learning but then
we've also uh as a community figured out
how self-supervised learning can be used
to train these models and get them to do
interesting
things and the third thing is we have a
lot more compute and I will talk about
this so this is uh actually going to be
one of the focus of my
talk uh and we also have scalable
architectures right so even if you have
lots of compute it doesn't really help
if uh the machine learning architectures
that we have don't scale and make use of
the compute that we have so that's
obviously like a very closely related
and important part so just to look at
compute itself so this is kind of like a
plot of various models all the way from
1985 to modern day and so what's
interesting here is I mean first of all
uh before GPU Computing which is this
left side of the plot over
here uh what you see is that um the
computer has been doubling every 24
months so this has been just standard M
law we' have been getting faster and
faster processes but there is this sort
of discontinuity where people figured
out that they could use gpus that were
originally designed for for graphics uh
they could use that to do machine
learning and so what you see here is
that the slope of the uh increase in per
in amount of compute available changes
quite significantly it becomes a lot
more
Steep and so here the compute starts
doubling every 3.4 months starting about
2012 or
so and then the third major aspect is
these set of models uh that we're
familiar with now the Transformer models
and you see that uh the comput has been
doubling every two months uh with with
these models so uh so it looks like
compute obviously plays a very very
major role in the AI capabilities that
we have but also the models that are
able to take advantage of this
computer so what happened since 2018
which is what uh uh which is when uh
this comput started doubling every two
months so one of the major advances in
2018 was uh a new scalable deep learning
architectures that were published uh
that actually was able to take use of
this or make use of the compute very
well and then a lot of engineering
effort and um money
spent uh actually getting these models
uh scaling up these models built on
these architectures right actually
making use of the computer and this is
kind of uh always a separate concern
because even if you have a great model
that scales really well there needs to
be like a lot of engineering done to
actually scale it
up and the scalable model that was
published in 2018 was the
Transformers so most of you might have
seen this
already so this is the paper attention
is all you need which was published in
two first published in
2017 and has already gotten tens of
thousands of citations if not more close
to 100,000 cations and uh this is an
architecture that replaced lstms which
were the dominant recurrent Network
architecture for sequence processing at
the
time so
um so there are various reasons why
Transformers are scalable uh and what
was kind of interesting is
that so they're scalable not just in the
ability to be able to run them across a
lot of gpus or to use up a lot of
compute but uh the important aspect of
scaling up over here is that as you
spent more compute uh the model
performance
improved right and that's that's a
really important aspect and this is kind
of the scaling plot from the now famous
uh gpt3 paper and what you see is uh on
the x-axis is the amount of compute that
was used to train the model so this kind
of includes a combination of the model
size and the uh length of the training
which is also like very closely related
to the amount of data that was available
and uh the y axis here is the validation
error and and what you see here is that
as you spend more and more compute as
you have larger models and as you train
them for longer uh with with certain
amounts of data the validation error
goes
down and uh so uh you can you can really
like invest comp and get
returns out of using using a poet comput
and here there's like a power law
relationship between these two and
depending upon the model more recently
people have observed there's like a much
more complicated relationship but these
models do tend to improve in performance
as you invest more compute in them uh up
till up to a certain limit
obviously okay so why do these uh
architecture scale well is I mean
obviously one of the main questions and
then by extension can we scale these
models even better and how do we do
this so to answer the question of why do
Transformers scale so well I mean there
are lots of reasons I'm just like
focusing on a few of them but uh like I
said Transformers were uh proposed as a
replacement to recurrent networks in the
form of
lstms and they use something called self
attention to process a quences so U what
they did was they replaced recurrent
networks which which are known to be
hard to train with feed forward networks
that are easier to train and uh the
other kind of very important U advantage
of Transformers was that they allow
parallelization across the length of the
sequence right and so when you have like
really long sequences or I mean any
number of sequences in any length of
sequence the recur Network you always
have to uh process it one SE sequence
element at a time and with Transformers
you could process the entire length of a
sequence in one go because of the
particular way the architecture is
designed and that's a pretty huge
Advantage because now you have a whole
new dimension of
parallelization and um so the second
reason why Transformers scale so well is
because uh we already figured out that
gpus work well for machine learning and
Transformers were really really uh great
fit for gpus right so you could a
Transformer and a GPU and really make
full use of the compute provided by the
GPU I mean we don't know if uh
Transformers are intrinsically better as
a model or if it is just because of the
good fit between Transformers and the
available compute U the available types
of compute that we have today so gpus
primarily so uh which is which is kind
of this uh question of was it a hardware
Lottery right um so a hardware Lottery
is used to describe when a research idea
wins because it is suited to the
available software and Hardware better
and not because the idea is superior to
the alternative research directions and
so for Transformers it's not fully clear
if it was just a hardware lottery or if
there's like something uh very
intrinsically advantageous about
it okay
so so so the scaling of Transformers I
mean I'm not going to go into any
further Det because there's a lot of uh
literature published on this but now the
question is can we scale even better
than Transformers and this is kind of a
plot U uh taken from this paper by uh
boan who's a professor in neuromorphic
professor in trans
Stanford and uh so this is a plot of the
uh on the x-axis you see the number of
neurons and y axis the energy
consumption right and uh so this Gray
Line over here is where we are at
currently so that's kind of the standard
silicon chips uh in
2D and U the
biological uh systems that we know of so
biological brains is this darker line
over here which kind of uh you see has a
much steeper slope of scaling compared
to the Silicon chips that we have so
I'll talk about what this line in
between is in a moment but
uh because of just like very practical
reasons just physical constraints and
the sizes of things and the amount of
energy that it can consume and just the
proportion of things like proportion of
wiring uh versus the amount of compute
that you have available so for various
different reasons you really want the
steeper slope uh in both the algorithms
and the hardware that you have because
otherwise it makes it like close to
impossible to achieve aieve the same
level of scale so over here biological
brains have reached like 86 billion
neurons and uh well I mean this is a
little bit uh older but this because of
the steep slope if you wanted to reach
the same number of units you're going to
consume quite a bit more energy right so
Transformers are probably like somewhere
up there and biological brains are over
here and at some point this becomes a
deal breaker so you can this this starts
like uh providing like an uh upper limit
on how big you can scale the models so
Energy Efficiency in that sense is like
uh like a very fundamentally important
uh aspect u i mean assuming that scaling
models always gives you this U dividend
of better performance then uh it it at
some point without efficient models it
becomes impossible to reach sizes that
can do interesting
things
okay so uh what does biology do how does
biology scale because we see that it has
this steep slope of scaling and one of
the things that it does is um it uses a
lot of sparity I mean a lot of it is
also again like just because of physical
limits and the amount
of uh cells the density of the cells
that you can have the amount of energy
available to the brain and so on
but mean since this has evolved under
these constraints what we have ended up
with are
uh is a substrate for computation that
is extremely sparse both in time and
space so uh this is kind of like a plot
of What U the neuron activity looks like
uh for for like one of these typical
neurons and what you usually see is that
there are these kind of spikes so there
are times when the neuron decides to
communicate with the rest of the neurons
and then most of the rest of the time
it's really not doing much and then so
you have like these spikes of outputs
and this is sparsity in time so um in
terms of activity and then you also have
sparsity in terms of space which is just
the connectivity of the neuron is very
very sparse so not all neurons in the
brain are connected to all the other
neurons so second thing is uh neurons uh
use event based
communication uh which means that
communication really happens only
through discrete events that send
messages between units and so it's not
the case that each neuron is talking
with the next neuron all the time right
which is uh on the other hand most of
our artificial neural networks really do
work like that so there's like an output
that goes to the next unit or the
connected units pretty much all the
time uh the third thing and again this
is because of just uh very practical
constraints in biology is that learning
is local in time and space so you cannot
uh have uh altw communication between
like neurons in the brain to do learning
because it's just
impractical and uh so what this means is
that each synapse has to use information
that's
available mostly locally to the synapse
and then with like very very low
dimensional Global signals incorporated
into this so uh and and and so this this
is par in uh is it's local in time as
well and the fourth aspect is uh temp
oral coding so because time is available
in some sense for free quote
unquote uh neurons can use time to
compute they can use time to actually
send
messages uh and it can be used in
various different ways uh so you can
neurons are able to trade off
computation for time in that sense there
are lots of other interesting properties
asynchrony for example uh and then also
some sort of like distributed learning
that happens in various parts of the
brain so I won't be talk going into
detail into any of those at the
moment okay so let's come back to this
plot which showed the scaling of various
things and so now I've added back the
labels from the original plot and so uh
this Gray Line over here is the dense 2D
silicon scaling that we have and so this
middle line over here is what would
happen if you actually took the silicon
and put it in three dimensions but
without sparity and so you you obviously
do get like better scaling but there are
some practical challenges that need to
be overcome to actually have
three-dimensional silicon uh mostly
related to heating
issues and uh the biological brains are
all in this regime of sparse
three-dimensional um substrates right so
this sparity is really what makes the
difference uh I mean given you have a
three dimensional substrate sparity is
really what makes a difference in uh
allowing this much better scaling
property of these U computational
devices as it
were so this really means that we need
uh apart from uh the right algorithms we
also need the right
hardware and uh there has been quite a
lot of work on biologically inspired
Hardware that can make use of the SP
asynchronous communicating neural
network units uh so uh and this is kind
of like this illustration uh that Intel
has so they they've been like also
working on one of the uh neuromorphic
Pro processors called lii and uh this is
like a really great illustration of like
the differences between conventional
Computing and neuromorphic Computing but
essentially in conventional Computing
you have synchronous clocking you have
sequential threads of control whereas in
neuromorphic Computing you have
completely asynchronous even based
spikes and parallel and sparse compute
and uh it's also I mean so gpus are kind
of in between so which allows parallel
Computing but it's still synchronous
clocking and it's kind of kind of more
optimized for dense
computation and uh so these neuromorphic
chips are essentially chips that use
these biological um ideas and are able
to work with
sparsity in both time and space and also
able to work with asynchronous
computition and so the state of the
neuromorphic chips right now just to
kind of uh summarize uh what's what's
been happening so I mean I I personally
don't work on the hardware aspect of it
but mostly in uh the algorithms but
there has been recable amount of
progress with neuromorphic chips so for
example um in 2021 at least uh so this
is like a plot which shows U the uh
relative performance of various uh
devices in comparison with this Intel
Loi chip which is a neuromorphic device
and uh so if a device is if a point is
above this dotted line it means that um
Loi the neuromorphic device does better
and if it's below it means the
conventional device does better and all
of the points here are conventional
devices so you have a CP you have CPUs
gpus
um some kind of like accelerator deep
learning accelerator and IBM True North
which is also a neuromorphic device but
a little bit older and uh the bat size
also makes a huge difference if you have
bat size of one the neuromorphic devices
tend to do better in general and larger
bat sizes
uh gpus T to do better and so uh so so
what you see over here is uh well first
of all uh there are certain like
biologically inspired models which are
these blue ones over here that do much
better on a neuromorphic device compared
to uh conventional
Hardware on the other hand uh what you
see is that even for some of these
biologically
inspired uh models if you start using
large patch sizes so if you look at this
purple Square over here uh it uses
something called an LSN which was one of
the uh papers that I was involved in uh
a few years ago and if you combine that
combine that with deep neural networks
for a bat size of one uh the
neuromorphic device does better but then
if you improve increase the batch sizes
then uh gpus suddenly start doing
better so uh so neuromorphic devices are
still not there yet it's still work in
progress and uh Loi for example is a
digital neuromorphic device and there's
lot of uh variety of possible
neuromorphic devices out there a lot of
people working on very cool interesting
ideas uh but there is this promise of uh
uh the neuromorphic devices having
really intrinsically better scaling
curves if the engineering is done
right okay so
now uh I'm going to talk about
algorithms a little bit so let's just go
back to this slide uh where we looked at
what biology does uh that uh I think is
important for scaling up these
models and uh one of the initial kind of
attempts at using some of these
principles was what are called spiking
neural
networks and uh spiking neural networks
are essentially a direct biological
uh I mean it's it's a model of a neuron
that is really directly uh derived from
biology so as I said in biology you have
neurons and then if you kind of stick
electrone in the neuron and measure
um uh measure what it's doing uh what
you see is that it has this action
potential right so it's suddenly there
is this surge uh this the sudden change
in like the potential and I'll tell you
what this potential is in a minute and
uh but this uh action potential as it's
called is a spike and uh that's what is
used for communicating and most of the
rest of the time the neuron doesn't do
much and so this action potential is
essentially uh because the neuron is
constructed in such a way that there is
a voltage potential difference between
the inside and outside of the neuron and
most of the U and this potential is kind
of uh constructed through uh the
movement of ions the neurons control the
movement of ions but across the membrane
across the cell membrane and which kind
of creates a membrane potential and this
is used to kind of trigger the action
potential of a neuron which leads to
ionic currents inside the neuron which
teaches the synapsis and then there's a
chemical messaging across the synapse
which goes to the next neuron and so on
so that's kind of like the biological
process and this can be simplified into
like like a circuit uh if you will an RC
circuit and then it can further be
simplified into a computational model
where uh there are in inputs coming in
as spikes which are just zero or one
values and the neuron does a weighted
sum of all the inputs coming in so this
is kind of very similar to what
artificial neural networks do except
that in the case of spiking neural
networks the inputs are binary and very
very sparse in
and uh so the neuron kind of integrates
this and then if the internal state of
the neuron goes above certain threshold
then it also emits a sparse discrete
Spike and uh so if
you uh kind of uh look at the activity
of the neuron this is what it looks like
so the membrane potential if if if there
is a input that looks like this so some
sort of uh constant input then the
membrane potential goes up every time a
SP Pike arrives at the cell body so in
this case just the neuron the
computational neuron and whenever this
membrane potential goes above a certain
threshold then the neuron emits a
spike right okay so this is a very very
simplified model and this model is
called The Leaky integrated and fire
model U so you can kind of write this
down in terms of equations and
essentially uh uh okay I mean so I I
don't think I will go through this but
um maybe the important thing to kind of
note is that uh there is some sort of uh
the output of the neuron which is Z over
here is one if the me internal membrane
potential is above thresold and zero if
it is not and this Zed is the only thing
that other neurons see so the membrane
potential is completely internal to this
neuron and no no other part of the model
has access to it uh but this one zero
value this binary value the spike that's
emitted is what uh the other neurons see
and this this kind of depends on the
threshold okay
so now uh spiking neurons are great
because you have this temporal sparity
now right so you're not like sending
messages all the time but you're only
sending messages every now and
then but uh you need to train these
models and in a standard RNN you can
just use back propagation Through Time
by defining a loss function and then
calculating the gradients of the loss
function back propagate It Through Time
into the model and then update the the
weights based on this gradient but the
problem with spiking neural networks is
that the spike emission function is non-
differentiable which means that it's not
so straightforward to just apply back
propagation Through Time
directly because that depends on all the
parts of the model being
differentiable but there is kind of like
this uh very crude trick as it were that
works surprisingly well uh that we
discovered uh back back in 2018 along
with colleagues which is that you can I
mean so this uh blue curve over here is
the spike emission function which is
this kind
of thres uh step function which where
the derivative is not defined at the
threshold and uh we kind of realized and
I mean a lot of people realized at
around the same time that you could just
Define a pseudo derivative so you could
Define a derivative at that point quite
AR
Lily and uh within within some
constraints if you uh so for example we
uh defined it in this uh P linear
function and uh it tends to work really
really well so you just replace the
derivatives of this uh non
differentiable function at that
particular point with the value that's
derived from the pseudo derivative and
then you can just train all these models
with back propagation through time and
they work work really great but turns
out that that's not enough I mean so if
you have spiking neuron and use back
propagation through time uh that's
really not enough to get the same level
of performance as artificial neur
networks because the second aspect of
recurrent networks that we needed was
long short-term memory and recurrent
networks uh need to have some sort of
memory by default U so just standard
artificial uh recurrent networks and
leaky integrated fire neurons neither of
them have this long shortterm memory so
in the uh deep Learning Community people
tended to use this model called
LSM uh which was really really powerful
because it had this specific mechanism
for storing and updating a me something
called a memory cell so it could U gate
the input coming into the memory cell it
could uh decide to forget things it
could also gate the things going out of
the memory cell and this really helped
uh this model to work really work
have have long memory essentially long
short-term
memory and so we wanted to do something
very similar for spiking neural networks
because leaky integrated fire neurons by
default do not have uh this memory and
so one of the interesting observations
uh that we had was that in
Neuroscience the activity of the neurons
don't really correspond to like a very
typical leaky integrated fire Neuron
model pi because there seems to be some
sort of adaptation happening so if
the neuron has constant input so I mean
this is this is kind of an example where
if if you give the neuron constant input
for leaky integrated fire neuron you
mostly expect the spikes to be evenly
spaced U because every time it hits the
threshold uh the neuron spikes and then
it's reset to a lower value and then the
input kind of drives the mem brain
potential up again it spikes again and
so on but what you actually see in
biology is some sort of adaptation so if
a neuron spikes then after every Spike
the next Spike uh is pushed back it it
spikes less for a while and then after
that uh it spikes again and then again
it spikes less for a while and SW on
there's kind of like adaptation of the
Dynamics uh and you see this everywhere
so in the pyramidal cells in the mouse
and in the human neocortex so this is
data from the Allen Institute where they
kind of characterize cells from various
different animals and um so this kind of
measure of this adaptation is called an
adaptation index and essentially what
you see is there's a big chunk of
neurons in uh humans and mice which are
which have an adaptation index that is
large which means that there is this
adaptation
happening and so what we did uh was to
try to model this uh and include this F
and leaky integrated neurons and we came
up with a model called uh an Adaptive
leaky integrated INF fire neuron where
the idea was quite simple it was uh to
adapt the threshold every time a spike
happened so every time a spike happened
the threshold would go up a little bit
and then DEC back to the base
value and so as it turned out this
simple mechanism so this this kind of
threshold adaptation was enough to uh
put the performance of spiking neurons
on like very very close to lstms when
trained with back propagation through
time so this is a plot where you see
this uh so this was uh tested on mnist a
sequential Mist where you give the uh
input one pixel at a time to the
recurrent Network and then it actually
to classify what the digit was at the
end and uh so just standard leaky
integrated fire neurons does really
really poorly so it has like 50% test
accuracy whereas just adding this
adaptive threshold which is the model
that we called LSN gets the performance
up to 93.7 right and lstms are up here
at
98% and um so with with some other
additions uh and using parameter
sparcity uh it goes up to 96.4 right and
this is with spiking neurons so it turns
out that uh so this this was like one
one example of like using like
biological data and basing the model on
that and seeing a huge Improvement in
what the models could
do okay uh so how am I doing on time uh
uh so we're about halfway through the
session now so how how long do you much
more do you think you'd
like um probably about 15 more minutes
is that okay we're halfway through the
hour H you can take an extra 15 more
minutes it means we'll have sort of 15
minutes for chat at the end so it's up
to you kind of how you want to uh divide
it I would like to remind everybody if
questions they can kind of jump in as we
go as well there's it's it's really
dense this one I'm loving it but like I
I guess yeah the timing we might have a
little bit less time for chat at the end
but if people want to stay on um the
call like I can stay on as well for a
bit longer if you can as well and and
yeah absolutely sure I mean yeah so I
will I will try to like uh do speed it
up a little bit at least like skip some
parts and then you can go and look up
the paper right okay don't go all the
details okay but uh so uh so we kind of
also had um um models that were able to
take advantage of this temporal coding
that I mentioned actually using time to
do computation and uh so to kind of
quickly uh summarized this the idea was
that so in the brain uh
you kind of have a specific mechanism
that controls the speed of transmission
of signals uh so this is called um um so
there's this thing called a milein
sheath and there's there's been like a
lot of recent evidence that uh so the
milin sheath is has been known to
control the speed of the signal
transmission there's been a lot of
recent evidence that the m and sheath
actually
adapts u in adults which means that that
seems to be like an additional dimension
of learning that happens in the
biological brain in adult brains and um
so we wanted to kind of see what can be
done with just controlling the speed of
transmission so which in a computational
model translates to a delay so a delay
in communication between one neuron and
another neuron and so what we tried to
do was to test out uh if we could train
a model with only synaptic delays uh
without training the weights at all and
see how far we could go on deep learning
benchmarks right and so we did this and
uh so we had like a temporal encoding
and we constrained the weights to only
three values so some so it was something
likeus 10 0 and plus 10 uh and the
weights were randomly initialized and
then fixed and then we trained only the
delays of the uh Network synaptic delays
and it was quite interesting to see that
just by training delays you can get
performance that's comparable to like
your standard uh both both uh standard
artificial neural networks uh without
convolutions and uh standard spiking
neural networks uh where the weights are
trint can I can I just ask is that with
the Adaptive neurons as well that you
were just talking about or is this just
with the
delay uh so this does have some form of
adaptation in the neuron uh so it's
actually a slightly different form but
in this particular case uh we were
working with feet forward networks and
not tricker networks okay so uh the
memory didn't matter so much okay thank
MH so this is an example of like using
uh time uh for computation and we
there's ongoing work to kind of extend
this even further and to see really how
far we can uh push using time as to
compute because so what is interesting
is uh when when you use delays for
example uh in a computational model if
it's implemented properly in appropriate
Hardware a delay is just uh a neuron not
doing anything until a certain point
right which means that when you're when
it's not really doing anything when it's
not sending um message to the following
neurons you're not consuming any energy
and so this is a very uh nice way to
make the models more efficient by tra by
having delays and uh by using by kind of
like reducing the activity of the
overall
Network
okay
so uh so so far we've been like looking
at at spiking neural network so which
were these models that were based kind
of like very very closely based on
biological Dynamics and uh still using
all of these principles of sparity and
event based communication and temporal
coding but spiking neural networks of
this particular form still don't work um
as well as the best deep uh Network
models so essentially in 2018 lstms were
when when we were doing this adap
neurons lsms were the dominant model but
then as we as I mentioned in the
beginning of the talk uh there have been
like newer models that have been
performing even even better and so now
we really have these Transformers and
related models that do really really
well and scale really really well and
spiking neural networks pretty soon kind
of hit a uh ceiling in terms of how well
they could do and we had to think about
uh ways to push the effectiveness of
these models beyond that while keeping
all the advantages in terms of sparcity
and
efficiency so we started thinking about
uh really using these principles
biological principles and designing
models uh from first principles uh to
take advantage of sparsity and event
driven Computing and so on but then
without really modeling the neuron
directly based on
biology uh and the I mean in for the
sparsity in time the basic idea really
was that you had like this threshold
gating function uh that would decide
when communication went uh to other
neurons and when it did not and we
realized that we could just put this use
this for other uh architectures that
tended to work really really well for
things like language modeling
so uh and and with both uh these models
and with spiking Dr networks what
happens is that uh because you have this
uh activity sparcity which is
essentially that not all the units are
active all the time when you train these
models the backward pass is also sparse
because you only really need to
propagate the gradients through the uh
units that were active and a few other
units because of the particular shape of
the pseudo derivative that we chose but
you do not have to propagate the
gradients through all the units and if
you can actually take have some Hardware
that can take advantage of this you end
up getting like way more efficient
training as well so not just the forward
bus so this is kind of uh uh an
illustration of this so the forward pass
over here with these blue arrows is uh
only goes through units that are active
and the backward pass uh when you're
calculating the gradients again only
goes to the units that are active and a
couple of other units uh that were close
to being active but most of the other
units are skipped entirely in this
computation and we decided to to take
this model called a gated recurrent unit
which is another recurrent Network model
that works uh quite well I mean it's
still lot on par with Transformers but
uh it works uh so mean it was it was one
of these models that had like a really
quantitative advantage over leaky
integrated Fire based spiking networks
and we wanted to make it activity sparse
as well and uh so we took the Gru and
added a even generating mechanism to it
using a gate and uh few a few other
features like having a reset and having
um refractory period and so on and with
this model we were actually quite easily
able to match the performance of lstms
or or like the best language models
recurrent language models u in terms of
perplexity so that's that's kind of like
what you see over here so there are like
two different data sets one is the
pentry pentry bank and one is the
wikitex 2 and the
uh bold values are like the best
recurrent Network model performance on
these two data sets and with our uh
event based Gru model as we called it we
were able to get um perplexities that
were very very close to these um
recurrent models but we had extremely
high activity sparcity right so if you
look at just maybe this one example uh
with the egru on the penry bank we had
about 80 85% activity sparcity and so if
you had had Hardware that could actually
take advantage of it it would uh it
would use like 85% less computation if
the hardware could actually take full
advantage of it and the backwards parity
was close to 50% so you really end up
doing like 50% less computation for
training the same model right and we
were also able to use like way fewer
parameters uh to do this so overall uh
these models I mean so the thing is this
these resarch that we showed uh all the
training was done on gpus because we
actually don't have the hardware that
can take advantage of all of this
sparsity uh but this is uh in some sense
like calculation of exactly how much
energy we would be able to save if we
had this
hardware and U so we we were we were
also kind of able to tune uh kind of
tradeoff uh sparity with performance
within certain limit so you see here
that we don't even though we are very
close to the recurrent model uh
performance we don't actually reach it
and then there is a way to kind of make
it less spse and reach this uh close and
you still kind of end up with some
Energy
savings uh so for example uh so we
actually implemented this on a
neuromorphic chip uh recently uh is a
neuromorphic chip called Spiner 2 which
is developed by uh some folks at T
Reston in Germany and what was kind of
interesting is uh in if you if the
energy consumption for single batch
uh for Spiner 2 which is this green bar
over here as you can see is
significantly lower than running it on a
GPU so uh this blue bar is the a100 GPU
which is like the one of the more recent
ones and the orange one is like a
slightly older GPU so it's like a little
bit slower and uh Spiner 2 and this was
like actually a very uh Proto uh the
implementation was essentially a
prototype so we were not actually making
full use of the chip but uh it was able
to make use of some of the sparity um on
the device and you kind of get like a
huge energy Advantage even with that
although for larger batches you don't
right so this is kind of still one of
the uh difficult areas of neuromorphic
computing where it's not able to take
advantage of lar larger batches so um
yeah so this is kind of uh on archive
you can go look look it up uh but uh so
we kind of like getting there slowly um
getting getting all of the sparsities on
Hardware okay so we can also use
sparsity to make training very efficient
I won't go into this in detail but
essentially you can use algorithms that
so far were considered
completely uh computationally
prohibitive uh in terms of the
computational expense you can actually
that so these algorithms uh become more
practical if there is activity sparsity
and parameter
sparity okay so so and we we have
explored like a really really really
tiny part of the properties that can
make model scalable which is just
activity sparity and parameter sparcity
and we have mostly explored it only in
terms of algorithms and so there's
obviously like a long way to go before
we start reaching this scaling uh of
biological uh substrates and biological
algorithms but we're kind of like trying
to move towards this direction so that's
kind of like the conclusion ution which
is that um sparity and locality are
essential for scaling up models due to
energy constraints and there might there
are also other clever ways to use
physical substrates uh to use to improve
Energy Efficiency so using time to
compute communication and others and the
next step is to really like try to scale
it up and start to catch up with uh
Transformer based models on tasks that
are a lot more closer to what people use
in the real world so a lot of this work
was done with lots of other people uh so
this is the group that uh group and
collaborators that we have we have like
a large group in ruer University bohome
so you might you some of you might have
actually seen a talk by David Capel who
gave a talk at mream a while ago so uh
and we have a few people from T Tron and
uh there's is the group that actually
develops the Spiner to hardware and
makes all of this possible so thank you
very much um yeah hopefully we have some
time for discussions thank you so much
that was absolutely fascinating there's
a lot to unpack there so Harris you've
got your hand up if you want to ask a
question yeah ER I just wanted to uh say
Kudos it was very interesting and I have
a couple of uh questions related to this
presentation uh first of all H you you
poed one um very interesting question
that has to do uh with the following um
can we scale even better let's say
moving effectively moving beyond
Transformers and as far as I understand
it uh because uh these large language
models the llms are very are all the
hype these days so as far as I
understand it not all llms are are
Transformers
uh but the other way around is true and
the reason for for that H is because uh
there are some um llms that are not
based in in
Transformers as you mentioned uh you
mention the recurrent neural networks of
course and that's one one type let's say
and uh another uh uh subtype that is is
based on rnet is
the long shortterm memory networks that
you are group is is actually
investigating and uh what I wanted to
say is
that trying to uh put everything
together is there a
possibility for moving beyond uh the
Transformers and scaling even better by
opting for what is called poly
Computing and and I mean poly Computing
that is capable to uh to combine uh
different types of computing in a multi
Computing Paradigm like classical
Computing Quantum comp Computing
neuromorphic and even Optical so what do
you think about
that yeah that's a very interesting
question I mean so there's definitely
like a lot of potential in these
unconventional Computing devices that
various people are developing right and
each of them have different strengths
and different
weaknesses so it would make sense to
combine them together in a way that uh
we use the strengths of like some of
them without uh being affected by their
weakness so much but uh well I mean at
least in terms of efficiency
itself if using like multiple devices or
multiple different uh Computing
nodes always kind of leads to this
problem where you do a lot of
communication and communication is
expensive right so even on a CPU or a
GPU or like most Computing devices that
we have today uh the communication is
really the bottleneck so that's probably
uh I mean that's actually like one of
the main reasons why we are looking at
activity sparsity because that's that
has to do with communication so
communication tends to take a lot of
energy it consumes a lot of time and so
uh when with like multiple different
types of commun computing the main
problem that would have that would need
to be solved is how do you make
communication
efficient both like on a physical
substrate you know like both both in
terms of like the device itself and also
in terms of
algorithms okay thank you thank you very
much um yeah I had a couple of questions
as well I think it's it's fascinating um
that you're saying essentially that you
can get get the same performance of the
lstms but like with about 80% less power
like I think that's really amazing do
you think that this these types of
architectures will be used sort of in
the near future to make say gpus more
efficient or or implemented in some
specific use cases maybe where sort of
the sort of temporal sparity is is
particularly important the temporal
coding is particularly important so I'm
quite interested to hear your take
console what the applications where you
see this being used in in the near
future MH so the temporal coding I mean
I've not really
seen uh much attempts to make use of it
I think it's it's probably like one of
those things which is like the hardest
to make use of both both from algorithms
and Hardware point of view but people
are trying to make use of uh this
activity sparity so Nvidia for example
recently uh added support for a certain
type of sparity like it's still like
very very limited but uh they started
adding support for a certain type of
sparcity which in principle could be
used for activities parity quite well
and there have also been like a couple
of deep learning accelerator companies
that uh do activities or I mean so okay
I mean so actually like the I mean
there's probably like a bit of context
that's required so the reason that
activity sparcity is really hard to make
use of in Hardware is because it's
Dynamic right so if you have parameter
sparcity and if the parameter spacity is
fixed you kind of know which uh
particular weights you need to load at
what times and which ones you don't but
if this is changing all the time then
it's really really hard to optimize uh
its use and so this Dynamic sparcity is
what is like extremely challenging for
gpus and like most conventional devices
so uh nvidia's attempt at adding this
support for sparcity is to to some
extent address uh being able to use
Dynamic sparcity although in's case you
cannot use uh I mean so basically using
even static spity is very very hard
unless it's designed in like a very
specific
way uh
so and and so this deep learning
accelerator company that I was
mentioning so they really have done
they've designed a chip completely from
scratch so it's a company called
cerebras which can make use of Dynamics
parcity and uh and it's also like super
scalable because essentially what
they've done is created like this huge
chip on a single wafer which means that
the communication overhead is much much
lower and uh it works like really really
great for training like extremely large
models if if you have the right kind of
sparcity on them right so it's still not
like completely general purpose it's
still like very closely tied to
Transformer architectures but it can use
activity sparcity really well uh if
implemented correctly but uh they don't
really go beyond that so they don't do
like time based Computing or make use of
like any of the other aspects especially
asynchronous Compu Computing for example
is as far as I know only
neuromorphic people working on
neuromorphic devices seem to even use it
although well I mean I guess like
somewhat ironically we haven't fully
figured out how to use it
effectively interest I was actually just
going to ask you a bit about Dynamics
vast because I'm in interested in um
sort of neuro neur taking inspiration
from neurod development and I I think
it's really interesting that in the
developing brand like say from about Age
2 to 10 you have huge amounts of
synaptic pruning like you actually lose
about 50% of your synapses and that's
essentially a a key component of how we
learn um so before I saw this talk I was
thinking about how if anyone's actually
taking inspiration from neurod
development for example thinking about
sparity and how the brain sort of
develops by pruning away all the sort of
unwanted connections is is that which is
people are thinking about does that fit
into what you were just saying a little
bit about Dynamics B here is that
slightly
different uh no I mean it's actually
very very closely related and uh I mean
we've been like thinking about it a
little bit also but so essentially uh
what we have come to realize is that so
there are two
different aspects to having a model that
performs well so one is just the
inference so if you have sparity uh you
can make predictions with this model or
like kind of run the model forward uh
and uh any sort of sparity helps it
makes it very very efficient but this
does not necessarily make the model easy
to
train right so you need to have there is
this like really orthogonal uh concern
where you need to be able to train the
model well and it's little bit in
conflict with having sparsity so like
one of the well at least like from a
very very non-expert perspective what it
seems like is this neuro development uh
this kind of like pruning that happens
it seems like there might be like a
learning phase where a certain type of
learning happens that is a lot harder to
do if the overall network was really
sparse and then you have this like huge
pruning space face uh and then you have
like a different network that learns
that can still learn but like a lot more
slowly perhaps or but but it's like a
lot more energy
efficient it interesting because yeah
like the brain although it's pruning
it's also growing and and the part of
the reason why it's growing so much is
because the myelination which is
interesting because you talk about that
in terms of the synaptic delays so maybe
sort of there's some balance between the
sparity pruning and then sort of the
delay marination that's introduced
somewhere in a dynamic way um that's
important to do I don't know yeah I mean
I think uh I mean yeah so I mean
obviously like in biology uh you know
like specific things don't just do one
thing right they do like a number of
different things so that's that's the
case with Malin as well for sure uh but
uh so kind of what what is interesting
is that with delays I mean if you can
control the delays and if you can work
with longer delays then you actually
need less activity in the network
because uh I mean so if you take like a
network with like absolutely no
long-term memory so like Ley integrated
F neuron or a v Network and you kind of
try to train this network to store
something for a longer time one of the
ways that it can discover to store
things is literally uh persistent
activity so you have like one neuron
that keeps firing all the time because
it's storing one particular bit of
information and then at the end if this
neuron is firing you know that bit is
stored and if not it's not right so it's
kind of I mean it doesn't always emerge
and it's pretty hard there's a reason
why these R networks don't work well for
like long-term memory but uh if you if
you make the problem simple enough you
do see this right and in when you train
like a spiking Network or an lstm you do
see like persistent activity on and off
for various things and if you had delays
you could just completely avoid this
right you could just like uh say this
neuron will will send the message when
it's ready after like a few time steps
or so and only then the other neuron
needs to process this
information okay interesting that might
touch on my which I'll make my final
question because we have to drop and
everyone's dropping off absolutely
unshare your screen sorry I should have
probably asked to do that earlier um I'm
I'm quite interested in this idea of so
artificial neural networks they have the
sort of this like always on an
activation function whereas people
contrast that with spiking neuron
networks which are like neurons and like
they're on or they're off and what's
interesting I guess from a neuroscience
perspective is because a lot of the
brain is actually gal cells which
actually do have more this continuous
Activation so the brain is actually
quite a hybrid between more like Anns
and snns essentially so I'm super
interested in sort of if if you think um
like maybe the future will be um hybrid
in some way um oh Carl Frist has entered
the way waiting room I think I'll ad
admit him I don't know if he's in the
right
meeting we're meant to have an sa
meeting
okay maybe yeah so that was my last and
final question sort of do you think the
hybrid system um would uh be something
which people are interested in or
looking at in the future or is that not
something that I see uh that's an
interesting question
so well I mean the qu I mean so I think
the related question that needs to be
answered is do hybrid systems really
provide any sort of advantage in terms
of uh computational Power or any any
other thing and at least like as far as
I know there is no reason I mean so if
you can get like this uh event based
system to work and at least like
theoretically it's they're like
equivalent they're supposed to be
equivalent to artificial like you know
non-even based systems then there
wouldn't be any reason to use a hybrid
system but it could very well be the
case that there are certain constraints
where just an even bit system would be a
way to slow or you know so that that
might be like a concern so it just like
takes too long to reach decisions or
something like that and then and then
you might need like hybrid systems as
well yeah I mean so I'm happy to discuss
I mean if you're interested in this area
I'm happy to discuss with you offline as
well I'm super interesting because as
well I like the sort of you get with the
gal cells there actually some electrical
communication they have Gap Junctions
and they have these sort of slow
oscillations which almost like f event
based oscillations almost take advantage
of or ride so there's sort of an
embedding nesting there of the the uh
spiking and non-spiking so um yeah it's
something I'm super interesting I don't
I just yeah I don't know if the Silicon
world is is as interested in it as me
though as a
neuroscientist yeah but I'm happy to chy
to it
offl okay well thank you so much that
was absolutely fascinating um I'm sure
people might want to reach out to you
with some questions s of offline because
this will be put on YouTube so if they
do what would be the best way for them
to contact you if that's okay yeah
absolutely it's okay I mean I have my
contact information on my website okay
great so email is probably like the best
way to contact me cool okay right thank
you so much and that's everything that I
have to cover um yeah thank you thank
you very much for inviting me to the
talk it was it was very interesting yeah
amazing yeah I'd love to stay in touch
and chat some more about this as well so
thank you so much
absolutely all right see you
byebye